Thomas Tarler

WORK EXPERIENCE

JANUARY 2022 - PRESENT

Sr. Data Scientist, FedNow Federal Reserve Bank of Boston

Designer and architectect behind the first AI systems for fraud detection on the FedNow Service

- Created, compiled, and executed on a five year plan to build a fraud score to be used in real-time transaction screening for the FedNow Service.
- Curated distinct fraud attack scenarios and designed controls that enabled all US banks to prevent fraud at their risk tolerance
- Catalyzed innovation through teams, brainstorming, education sessions, and other items to lead the first AI services ever deployed by the US Central Bank on \$1T+ in transactions

AUGUST- 2018 - DECEMBER 2021

Chief Data Scientist, Atlanta TSYS, a Global Payments Company

Created first Data Science team and overall Research and Development program within TSYS. Primary focus is in Fraud & Risk with mandate to develop into other portfolio areas.

- Championed and developed new products in the fraud and risk space which have created \$10M+ USD in net new revenue to the 2022 sales pipeline
- Partnered with consulting teams and product to build a consulting-into-innovation portfolio to better establish client needs and evaluate proposed products at an early stage
- Recruited and managed team of six data scientists over two years ranging from entry level to seniors
- Established program, team, and platform for rapid data science innovation Retooled for a consulting service with potential \$2M annual run rate.
- Assisted in managing the TSYS Foresight Score as the primary data scientist advisor - established MRM/SRII-7 practices and grew program from three client banks to over twenty clients and \$50M+ revenues
- Designed and constructed the TSYS R&D Data Lake at a total cost of \$300K - by far the single most efficient asset in TSYS history with \$2.5M USD in realized income

PUBLICATIONS

US20210042824A1

"Methods, Systems, and Apparatuses for improved fraud detection and reduction" U.S. Pat. US 2021/0042824A1" USPTO

https://patents.google.com/patent/

3390 Straford RD NE Apt 1016 +1 (720)496-9222 ttarler@gmail.com

SUMMARY

A top data scientist in credit card industry with experience in acquiring and issuing and an expert in fraud and real time authorizations with many of my ML prototypes in production use. I regularly transform limited budgets and informal influence into tightly focused projects with very large ROI. Skilled communicator, seller, leader, and visionary I often champion initiates with direct reporting lines into the President of TSYS Issuing from top-dollar sales efforts to M&A efforts and vendor management.

EDUCATION

2011 - 2015 Bachelor of Arts

With Distinction and Cum Laude
MATHMEMATICS AND ECONOMICS
University of Denver

2017 - 2020 **Master of Science**

DATA SCIENCE, WITH HONORS
Regis University

MAJOR PROJECTS

TSYS Advanced Decisioning

Internal Tools for Client Consulting to make fraud detection automated - to date has reduced clients net fraud losses by average of 13.2% Designed and implemented TSYS Data Science Platform, our first and only prototyping platform to enable rapid product testing and refinement.

TSYS Data Science Platform

Techniques

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Machine learning, Deep Reinforcment Learning, DevOps, Agile, financial forecasting, reinforcement/policy learning, data visualization, data wrangling, anomaly detection, data mining, event streaming, risk estimation and optimization

Technology

SQL, PYTHON, R, Tableau,
Hadoop, Spark, big data,
mainframes, non-stop
systems, ERP